Jacquelyn A. Ottman Collection of J. Ottmann Lithographing Company 1880-1920 (bulk 1880-1890) PR 281
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Jacquelyn A. Ottman Collection of J. Ottmann Lithographing Company
1880-1920 (Bulk 1880-1890)
PR 281
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.5 Linear feet
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Jacquelyn A. Ottman in January, 2010.
Bibliography
J. Ottman Consulting, Inc. "J. Ottman Consulting Celebrates J. Ottmann Lithographing". New York, J. Ottman Consulting, 2009.
"Large Fire in Warren Street", New York Times. 17 Mar, 1882:8
Last, Jay T. The Color Explosion: Nineteenth-Century American Lithography. Santa Ana, CA: Hillcrest Press, 2005:112-113.
"Notable Manufacturers", King's Handbook of New York City. Ed., Moses King. Boston: Moses King, 1892:885.
Biographical Note
Jacob Ottmann was born in Meisenheim, Prussia in 1849 and immigrated to New York with his mother and seven brothers and sisters in the 1860's. The only brother not to join his uncle's Fulton-market meat business, Jacob began his lithographic career around 1870, as a clerk at Ferdinand Mayer & Company. A few years later, in 1874, Ottmann signed on as junior partner with a firm started by Vincent Mayer and August Merkel, located at 22-24 Church Street; the firm was then renamed Mayer Merkel & Ottmann. In 1879 Mayer Merkel & Ottmann moved to 21-25 Warren Street, which was also the business location of the firm's most renowned client, Puck magazine -- the first weekly magazine in America to offer color illustrations.
In addition to printing the cartoons of Puck, the firm attracted a wide variety of other commercial clients. Indeed, according to The Color Explosion by Jay T. Last (Hillcrest Press, 2005),
By the mid-1800's Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann had become one of the largest American lithographic firms. They did a wide variety of work, including advertising posters, pamphlets and reproductions of oil and watercolor paintings. In the 1880's and 1890's Mayer Merkel & Ottmann shared the honor with the Donaldson Brothers of being the largest American trade card producers. In contrast to most trade card lithographers, Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann made practically no stock cards, but instead produced specially designed cards for individual advertisers. The varied designs documented everyday life in America.
In 1885, Mayer and Merkel retired from the firm and Ottmann took over the business, renaming it J. Ottmann Lithographing Company. That same year Ottmann joined with the publishers of Puck magazine, Joseph Keppler and Adolph Schwarzmann, to commission construction of a new office building on Houston Street. By 1886, the Puck Building, today a New York City historic landmark, was ready for occupation. Four years later, at the age of 41, Ottmann died. The J. Ottmann Lithographing Company continued in business until the first decade of the 20th century, after which it was merged into the United States Printing & Lithographing Company.
Scope and Content
The Jacquelyn A. Ottman Collection of J. Ottmann Lithographing Company contains 106 print items. The bulk of the collection is comprised of complete issues of, and tear sheets from, Puck magazine.
Puck was founded in 1871 in St. Louis by Josef Ferdinand Keppler, an Austrian-born cartoonist and caricaturist (and amateur actor). Named for Puck, the impish character celebrated by Shakespeare in "A Midsummer Night's Dream", it began as a weekly humor magazine and was the first magazine in America to offer color illustrations. After the magazine's initial run in St. Louis as a single sheet proved unsuccessful, Keppler moved to New York City. In September 1876, the first Puck magazine was printed in New York City in German on the presses of Mayer, Merkel and Ottmann (later J. Ottmann Lithographing). An English version followed in March 1877.
The first issues were printed on a plain black press, followed by simple and then increasingly more complex multichromatics. Eventually, Puck evolved into a thirty-two page issue which sold for ten cents. Each issue contained a full-color political cartoon on the front cover and a color non-political cartoon or comic strip on the back cover. There was always a double-page centerfold, usually on a political topic. Inside, numerous black and white cartoons illustrated the humorous anecdotes, fiction, non-fiction, poetry, and editorials. In addition to co-publisher Keppler, the group of cartoonists included Dalyrymple, C.J. Taylor, F.M. Howarth, Fred Opper and J.S. Pughe. The last few pages contained ads. Examples of all of these types of illustrations will be found in this collection.
The collection also includes a few examples of the wide variety of other work produced by Jacob Ottmann, including games, toys, advertising cards, and topical postcards. These items were collected over the course of three decades by Ottmann's great-niece, Jacquelyn Ottman. Many pieces in this collection were part of the exhibit, "J. Ottman Consulting Celebrates J. Ottmann Lithographing" at the Puck Building, September 14-24, 2009. More information on the exhibit and specific pieces in the collection can be found in the collection file, held in the Print Room.
Arrangement
The material is arranged chronologically. Where exact dates are not available, the items are arranged by the name of the printing company. Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann at Warren St. are circa 1880-1885. Items printed by "J. Ottmann Litho. Co." at the Puck Building are post 1885.
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I. Complete Magazines in both German and English languages
Series 2. Tear Sheets from the magazines
Series 3. Toys and Games
Series 4. Trade cards, Postcards and one photochrom print.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds The Joseph Keppler Cartoon Collection (PR 29) containing original lithographs by Keppler for Puck magazine.
Dalrymple, Louis; Keppler, Joseph Ferdinand -- Pictorial works; Opper, Frederick Burr; Pughe, J.S.; Taylor, Charles Jay; Advertising cards; Card games; Chromolithography; Paper dolls; Periodical covers; Periodicals; Photochrom prints; Postcards; Tear sheets
- Series I. German language Magazines (complete)
  - Subseries I. Puck
    - Aug 8, V. 12, No. 48, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aug 22, V. 12, No. 50, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dec 12, V. 13, No. 14, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Oct 16, V. 14, No. 6, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mar 25, V. 15, No. 29, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Nov 22, V. 18, No. 12, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Feb 19, V. 20, No. 25, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II. Puck Illustrated
    - Jan 19, V. 5, No. 18, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aug 10, V. 5, No. 47, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aug 31, V. 5, No. 50, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dec 27, V. 7, No. 15, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - May 7, V. 8, No. 34, 1884; All cover cartoons by F. Opper. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II. English language Magazines (complete)
  - Subseries I: Puck
    - Jan 16, Vol. XXIV, No. 619, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan 23, Vol.XXXVI, No. 933, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Feb 6, Vol. XXXVI, No.935, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan 2, Vol. XLVIII, No. 1243, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Feb 6, Vol XLVIII, No. 1248 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II. Puck's Library
    - Jan, No.114, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jul, No.132 (Cover only), 1898 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries III. Puck's Monthly Magazine and Almanac, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aug, No. 80, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III. Tear Sheets from Puck Magazine
  Arrangement Note
  Where specific dates of tear sheets are unknown, items are arranged by printing company. Mayer Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren St. indicate dates pre-1885. After this time, J. Ottmann moved the company to the Puck Building and formed J. Ottmann Lithographing Co.
  - Subseries I. Front Covers
    - Jul 21,Vol. VII, No. 176, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sep 1, Vol VII, No.182, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sep 22, Vol. VIII, No. 185, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jul 4, Vol. XXIII, No. 591, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan 23, Vol. XXIV, No. 620, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 6, Vol. XXIV, No. 622, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 13, Vol. XXIV, No. 623, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 20, Vol. XXIV, No. 624, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 27, Vol. XXV, No. 625, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mar 13, Vol XXV, No. 627, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mar 20, Vol. XXV, No. 628, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mar 27, Vol XXV, No. 629, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 5, Vol. XXVI, No. 674, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan 2, No. 930, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II. Back Covers
    - Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren St., New York (6), circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - J. Ottmann Lith. Puck Building, N.Y. (23), circa 1888 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III. Centerfolds, circa 1885-1889
    - Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren St., New York (2), circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - J. Ottmann Lith. Puck Building, N.Y. (9), circa 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IV. Miscellaneous, circa 1880-1890's
    - Puckograph (Mayer Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren Street, New York), circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Partial magazine with Centerfold (J. Ottmann Lith. Puck Building, N.Y.), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series IV. Toys/Games
  Advertising cards; Chromolithography; Paper dolls; Periodical covers; Periodicals; Politicians; Postcards; Tariff -- United States.; Tear sheets
  - Game of Peter Coddles, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Teddy Bear Paper Doll Kit (2), circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Game of Rex, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series V. Cards and Photochrom Print, circa 1890's
  - Subseries I. Advertising Cards, circa 1890's
    - J. Ottmann Lithographing Company, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Singer Manufacturing Company, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Wheeler & Wilson Sewing Machines, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - New Home Sewing Machine Co., circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Clark's Spool Cotton, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Charles Hires Company, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Franco American Food Co., circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Phillips & Clark Stove Company, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Smith & Anthony Stove Company, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Spicers & Peckham, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Gold Coin Stoves and Gold Medal Ranges (Bussey & McLeod Stove Co./ Gold Medal Base Burner (J.W. Doubleday & Co.), circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries II. Post Cards, circa 1890's
    - Artist signed - F. Foutcault (4), circa 1890's (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Christmas Greetings (2), circa 1890's (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous (1), circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Keppler, Joseph Ferdinand -- Pictorial works; Advertising cards; Card games; Chromolithography; Paper dolls; Periodical covers; Periodicals; Photochrom prints; political cartoons; Postcards; Tear sheets
  - Subseries III. Photochrom Print, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Schuylkill River" (Box 1, Folder 11)